You are watching a victim get scanned.
One of thousands of Americans caught in
a growing global crime spree.
That's no secret to police.
Or even store clerks
from Georgia.
to Massachusetts.
And Ohio,
I even talk to one of these scammers.
And you'll see how he tried to steal
ten grand. This is a scam.
You know it, and I know it.
in all of these cases.
These machines, called crypto ATMs,
become the getaway car
for the scammers who prey on victims
like Gus Cason.
That's where I stepped in $100 bills.
They would prompt you for everything
come up. And I had him on the phone to.
Had you ever seen this before?
Never been here before.
Never been here after.
Just outside
Cedar Rapids, Iowa, is where
Gus Cason calls home.
Raspberry, age 71, a retired union worker
and superfan of the band Nickelback.
Two years ago,
as he was recovering from a stroke.
I got a phone call
when he told me
he was president of the bank.
So now you tell me.
I want you to swear you're not a scam.
I swear I'm not a scam. You know that.
He convinced me he was good.
He was good.
I just had a stroke.
I wasn't thinking right at all.
The scammer told Gus
that he would be arrested
unless he withdrew $15,000 in cash
and deposited it in that crypto ATM.
It looks like a normal ATM,
but a crypto ATM is different.
Put in cash
and it converts it
into cryptocurrency in an instant.
Victims like Gus
have lost
about $240 million so far this year, says
the FBI.
Double the pace of last year.
I should've known better.
I should have known better.
I was stupid enough.
I fell for it.
The scammer took off with Gus's cash
in the form of cryptocurrency,
but the crypto ATM company also made
money from the transaction.
Our investigation found the
companies that operate crypto ATMs
profit off the fees and markups,
often at 20 to 30%
that they charge
on transactions, scam or legit.
And when police have seized
scammed cash out of the ATMs,
the crypto ATM companies
hit back
hard in court to get that cash back.
Which is what happened to Gus Cason
This is our evidence processing room.
Major Chad Colson
and his deputies at the Linn
County Sheriff's
Office managed to recover the $15,000
in cash
that Gus had
put into that crypto ATM
as evidence in a crime.
How confident are you
that the victim will get that money back
after you took it out of the machine?
So we were very confident.
His confidence was short lived.
Bitcoin depot,
the company with the most crypto
ATMs in the U.S.,
fought in court to get the $15,000 back.
The company points out its machines,
like many crypto ATMs,
have multiple on screen
warnings, alerts of scams
and requires that customers agree
that they're only sending money
to their own accounts.
So in court, Bitcoin Depot won.
We ended up getting, communication
from Bitcoin Depot.
They said it was a glorious day.
Gentlemen,
when can we come get our money?
Which was our victim's money?
A multi-million
dollar company is overjoyed
that they get $15,000 and our victim is,
you know, hurting.
I mean, that's their life savings.
Bitcoin depot
has used tough tactics
to stop police
from seizing money for evidence,
like threats to immediately
litigate or suspending fee refunds
in entire states of a single officer
tries to seize cash.
Bitcoin depot even sent an Amazon gift
to mock one police department
a copy of the U.S.
Constitution, with a note calling
the seizure of the scam victim's money
a Fourth Amendment violation.
After we reached out to Bitcoin Depot
about these messages to police,
the company told us
the messages were unacceptable
and the employee responsible
is no longer with Bitcoin Depot.
What do you think, Gus?
But everybody seemed to get money.
But you who save that money.
You know
Bitcoin had no business
getting that money at all.
I mean, really,
when especially when it’s a scam.
Do you think that's fair? Well, hell no.
Lawsuits from attorneys
general accused
the top three crypto
ATM firms of profiting from scams
and not protecting customers.
Iowa's AG more than half of all money
taken in by Bitcoin
Depot in Iowa over
three years came from scams.
Washington, DC's
AG at least 93% of deposits over
several months from Athena
Bitcoin machines came from scams.
Athena
Bitcoin tells CNN it strongly
disputes the allegations in the complaint
and says it has strong
safeguards against fraud.
Bitcoin depot tells us
we do not profit from scams, and the vast
majority of our customers
use our kiosks for lawful purposes.
The company adds
if it can't stop the transaction,
it reviews every potential scam case
individually for possible
fee relief or refunds.
But we spoke to nearly a dozen victims
who were tricked by scammers
while using Bitcoin depot machines.
And only one said she got a fee refund.
So this one is a popular spot.
Very popular.
Woodbury, Minnesota police
detective Lynn Lawrence.
We're just checking out.
The Bitcoin
machine is on the front line
of battling crypto ATM scams in her
Minneapolis suburb.
You have seen people at this machine?
Yes. Getting scammed? Yeah.
In the middle of a scam? Yep.
And they pump the money in?
Yeah.
It looks like they're at the casino
just shoveling it in.
Multiple local law enforcement
agencies tell us crypto
ATM companies
could do more to stop the scams.
Are they making money off of crime?
Absolutely they are.
What would you say to these companies?
Do better?
Do better,
because you're doing
a disservice to so many people.
And if you can put cigarets
behind the counter,
why can't you put the Bitcoin machine
behind the counter?
The Woodbury
police say the reason why scam
victims are almost
always out of luck
is because of crypto speed and anonymity.
Then, skipping from wallet address
to wallet address as it moves on.
Detective Lucas Rogers tracks
scam patterns
that start at crypto ATMs
in his Minnesota town.
This is,
pretty indicative of,
like, money
laundering type behavior,
where transactions are one by one
kind of peeling into,
an overseas exchange.
Those yellow dots are overseas
exchanges on the continent of Asia.
The different parts of Asia.
Yep, yup.
How long does this take?
Once the money is entered
into the machine in a matter of mere
seconds to minutes.
This money
can basically go anywhere in the globe.
This specifically is organized crime
not occurring here in the US.
That crime
sounds like this
What you’re watching is a scammer
trying to steal money from me.
We called what appeared to be a U.S.
phone number
on this official looking bill
that was emailed by the con artists.
in this scam.
The false claim
is that this company refunded me
too much money,
and I must send it back
to avoid committing a crime.
Oh no no no no no.
What happened that says 10,000?
Okay, I'm walking now.
I'm going to go to the car
What should I call my husband?
He wants to see proof.
Take. Take a picture of the money.
The scammer tells me where to go
to find the nearest machine
to deposit the money.
A yellow colored ATM machine.
I'm not going to put the money
into the machine.
Because this is a scam.
You know it and I know it.
You were talking to a reporter from CNN.
How much crypto money
are you transferring through?
Various electronic wallets?
Do you care about these people
you're scamming?
You do care?
Because a
lot of people
are losing their life savings.
Elderly people who fall for this.
Why do you keep doing it?